I am no designer, nope, no way.
أنا لست مصمما، أبدا، مستحيل.
My dad was,
والدي كان كذلك،
which is kind of an interesting way to grow up.
وذلك كان أمرا مثيرًا للاهتمام كلما تقدمت في العمر منذ صغري.
I had to figure out what it is my dad did
كنت أود معرفة ما يفعله والدي،
and why it was important.
ولماذا ما كان يفعله مهما.
Dad talked a lot about bad design when we were growing up,
كان والدي يتحدث كثيرا عن التصميمات السيئة،
you know, "Bad design is just people not thinking, John," he would say
كان يقول أشياء كـ"التصميم السيء يخرج من ناس لا يفكرون يا جون،
whenever a kid would be injured by a rotary lawn mower
عندما يصاب طفل بسبب مكينة قطع عشب دوارة،
or, say, a typewriter ribbon would get tangled
أو عندما تنعقد شريطة من آلة كاتبة،
or an eggbeater would get jammed in the kitchen.
أو عندما تعلق خفاقة البيض عند استخدامها في المطبخ،
You know, "Design -- bad design, there's just no excuse for it.
إنه التصميم، التصميم السيء، وهذا أمر لا مبرر له،
It's letting stuff happen without thinking about it.
هذا يحدث عند صنع الأشياء دون التفكير في ذلك،
Every object should be about something, John.
كل شيء مصمم يجب أن يُربط بشيء ما يا جون،
It should imagine a user.
يجب أن يُتخيل مستخدم لذلك الشيء،
It should cast that user in a story starring the user and the object.
ويجب أن يوضع المُستخدم والشيء المصمم في قالب قصصي يحكيهما،
Good design," my dad said, "is about supplying intent."
التصميم الجيد،" كما يقول والدي "يعتمد على إيصال النيّة"،
That's what he said.
هذا ما قاله.
Dad helped design the control panels for the IBM 360 computer.
ساهم والدي في تصميم لوحات تحكم حاسوب آي بي إم 360،
That was a big deal; that was important. He worked for Kodak for a while; that was important.
كان ذلك أمرا كبيرا، كان ذلك أمرا مهما، عمل والدي أيضا لدى شركة كوداك لفترة، وكان ذلك مهما،
He designed chairs and desks and other office equipment for Steelcase; that was important.
صمم والدي كراسي وطاولات وتجهيزات مكتبية أخرى لشركة ستيلكيس، وكان ذلك مهما.
I knew design was important in my house because, for heaven's sake, it put food on our table, right?
كنت أعي تماما أهمية التصميم في منزلي لأنه، وبحق السماء، ما يجلب الطعام على مائدة منزلنا، حسنا؟
And design was in everything my dad did.
فالتصميم كان داخلا في كل ما يفعله والدي،
He had a Dixieland jazz band when we were growing up,
كان لديه فرقة جاز موسيقية من نوع ديكسيلاند أثناء ما كنا صغارا،
and he would always cover Louis Armstrong tunes.
وكان دائما ما يحاكي ألحان لويس آرمسترونج،
And I would ask him every once in a while,
وكنت دائما أسأله من وقت لآخر:
"Dad, do you want it to sound like the record?"
"والدي، هل تود أن يكون الأداء التي تقوم به مثل التسجيلات الرسمية؟"
We had lots of old jazz records lying around the house.
كان لدينا الكثير من تسجيلات الجاز القديمة تلوح في أرجاء منزلنا،
And he said, "No, never, John, never.
وقال لي والدي "لا، أبدا ياجون، أبدا،
The song is just a given, that's how you have to think about it.
إن الأغنية أمر معطى فقط، وهكذا يجب أن تنظر لها،
You gotta make it your own. You gotta design it.
يجب أن تحولها إلى شيء يخصك، يجب أن تصممها،
Show everyone what you intend," is what he said.
اري الجميع ما تنوي فعله"، هذا ما قاله:
"Doing that, acting by design, is what we all should be doing.
"قم بذلك، وأنت تمارس التصميم، وهذا ما يجب على الجميع منا فعله،
It's where we all belong."
هنا ينتمي الجميع منا".
All of us? Designers?
جميعنا؟ مصممون؟
Oh, oh, Dad. Oh, Dad.
أوه، أوه يا والدي، أوه يا والدي.
The song is just a given.
الأغنية شيء معطى فقط،
It's how you cover it that matters.
وطريقة أدائك لها هو ما يهم،
Well, let's hold on to that thought for just a minute.
حسنا، دعنا نفكر في هذا الأمر قليلا،
It's kind of like this wheelchair I'm in, right?
إنه كالكرسي المتحرك الذي أجلس عليه الآن، حسنا؟
The original tune? It's a little scary.
اللحن الأصلي؟ إنه لأمر مخيف،
"Ooh, what happened to that dude?
"أووه، ما الذي حصل لذلك الشخص؟
He can't walk. Anybody know the story?
إنه لا يستطيع المشي، هل يعرف أحد ما القصة؟
Anybody?"
أي أحد؟".
I don't like to talk about this very much, but I'll tell you guys the story today.
لا أحب التحدث عن هذا الشأن كثيرا، ولكني سأخبركم بالقصة اليوم.
All right, exactly 36 years ago this week, that's right,
حسنا، منذ 36 عاما تماما مقابل هذا الأسبوع، حسنا،
I was in a poorly designed automobile
كنت أمتطي سيارة مصممة بشكل شيء،
that hit a poorly designed guardrail
وقد اصطدمت بحاجز طريق مصمم بشكل سيء،
on a poorly designed road in Pennsylvania,
على طريق مصمم بشكل سيء في ولاية بنسلفانيا،
and plummeted down a 200-foot embankment
وترديت وهويت 200 قدما للأسفل،
and killed two people in the car.
وتسببت في وفاة شخصين كانا في تلك السيارة،
But ever since then, the wheelchair has been a given in my life.
ومنذ ذلك الوقت والكرسي المتحرك أمر معطى في حياتي،
My life, at the mercy of good design and bad design.
حياتي، تحت رحمة التصميم الجيد والتصميم السيء.
Think about it. Now, in design terms,
فكروا في الأمر جيدا، من ناحية تصميمية،
a wheelchair is a very difficult object.
الكرسي المتحرك أداة عصيبة للغاية،
It mostly projects tragedy and fear and misfortune,
غالبا ما تصور الأسى والخوف والمصيبة،
and it projects that message, that story, so strongly
وغالبا ما تصور تلك الرسالة، تلك القصة، بشدة،
that it almost blots out anything else.
والتي تبعد كل احتمال آخر كالبقع التي تملأ المكان.
I roll swiftly through an airport, right?
يمكنني المرور بسهولة في المطار، أليس كذلك؟
And moms grab their kids out of the way and say, "Don't stare!"
وتقوم الأمهات بإبعاد أطفالهن عن الطريق وتقلن أشياء كـ"لا تحدق!"،
The poor kid, you know, has this terrified look on his face, God knows what they think.
ذلك الطفل، كما تعلمون، على وجهه نظرة خوف شديد، والله يعلم بما يفكرون،
And for decades, I'm going,
ولعقود وأنا أفكر:
why does this happen? What can I do about it? How can I change this? I mean there must be something.
لماذا يحدث ذلك؟ ماذا يمكنني فعله بشأن ذلك؟ كيف يمكنني تغيير ذلك؟ أقصد، يجب أن يكون هنالك شيء ما،
So I would roll, I'd make no eye contact -- just kinda frown, right?
لدى أغض بصري، ولا أنظر وأظل عابسا، حسنا؟
Or I'd dress up really, really sharply or something.
أو قد أرتدي شيئا أنيقا أو شيئا من هذا القبيل،
Or I'd make eye contact with everyone --
أو قد أنظر للجميع،
that was really creepy; that didn't work at all.
كان ذلك مريبا، ولن ينفع أبدا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You know anything, I'd try. I wouldn't shower for a week -- nothing worked.
حسنا، كنت أجرب كل شيء، قد لا أستحم لأسبوع... ولم يفلح شيء،
Nothing whatsoever worked until a few years ago,
لم يفلح شيء إلا قبل سنوات قليلة،
my six-year-old daughters were looking at this wheelchair catalog that I had, and they said,
ابنتاي اللتان تبلغان من العمر 6 سنوات كانتا تنظران لكتيب خاص بالكرسي المتحركة كان بحوزتي، وقالتا لي:
"Oh, Dad! Dad! Look, you gotta get these, these flashy wheels -- you gotta get 'em!"
"أوه، أبي! أبي! أنظر، يجب عليك الحصول على هذه، هذه العجلات المضيئة، يجب عليك الحصول عليها!"
And I said, "Oh, girls, Dad is a very important journalist,
وقلت لهما: "أوه، يا بنات، والدكن إعلامي مهم جدا،
that just wouldn't do at all."
وهذا لا يناسبه على الإطلاق".
And of course, they immediately concluded,
وبالطبع حكما في الحال بالآتي:
"Oh, what a bummer, Dad. Journalists aren't allowed to have flashy wheels.
"أوه، يا لها من مشكلة يا أبي، لا يمكن للصحفيين الحصول على عجلات مضيئة،
I mean, how important could you be then?" they said.
أعني، لأي درجة أنت مهم إذن؟" قالتا لي.
I went, "Wait a minute, all right, right -- I'll get the wheels." Purely out of protest,
وقلت: "انتظرا دقيقة، حسنا حسنا... سوف أحصل على هذه العجلات"، فقط لأجل التخلص من اعتراضهما،
I got the flashy wheels, and I installed them and --
حصلت على تلك العجلات المضيئة، وقمت بتركيبها،
check this out. Could I have my special light cue please?
أنظروا إلى ذلك، هل تسمحون لي بأخذ جولتي الضوئية الخاصة من فضلكم؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Look at that!
انظروا إلى ذلك!
Now ... look at, look at this! Look at this!
الآن... انظروا، انظروا إلى هذا! انظروا إلى هذا!
So what you are looking at here
حسنا، ما تنظرون إليه الآن
has completely changed my life,
غير حياتي تماما،
I mean totally changed my life.
أعني أنه غير حياتي تماما.
Instead of blank stares and awkwardness,
بدلا من النظرات الفارغة والإحراج،
now it is pointing and smiling!
أصبحت أحصل على إشارات وابتسامات!
People going, "Awesome wheels, dude! Those are awesome!
يقول الناس: "عجلات رائعة، يا رجل! إنها رائعة!
I mean, I want some of those wheels!" Little kids say,
أعني، أريد تلك العجلات"، يقول الأطفال:
"Can I have a ride?"
"هل يمكنني الركوب؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And of course there's the occasional person --
وطبعا هنالك شخص يأتي من وقت لآخر
usually a middle-aged male who will say,
وغالبا ما يكون رجلا في منتصف العمر قائلا:
"Oh, those wheels are great!
"أوه، هذه العجلات عظيمة!
I guess they're for safety, right?"
أعتقد أنها عجلات وقائية، أليس كذلك؟".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
No! They're not for safety.
لا، إنها ليست عجلات وقائية.
No, no, no, no, no.
لا لا لا لا لا.
What's the difference here,
ما الفرق هنا
the wheelchair with no lights
بين الكرسي المتحرك بدون الأضواء
and the wheelchair with lights?
والكرسي المتحرك بالأضواء؟
The difference is intent.
الفرق هو النيّة.
That's right, that's right; I'm no longer a victim.
هذا صحيح، هذا صحيح، لم أعد مجرد ضحية،
I chose to change the situation -- I'm the Commander of the Starship Wheelchair with the phaser wheels in the front. Right?
قررت أن أغير وضعي، أنا الآن قائد كرسي سفينة الفضاء مع عجلات الـ"فيزر" الأمامية، حسنا؟
Intent changes the picture completely.
النيّة تغير الصورة تماما،
I choose to enhance
قررت تعزيز
this rolling experience
حركة الدوران هذه
with a simple design element.
باستخدام عامل تصميمي بسيط،
Acting with intent.
عاملا بالنيّة،
It conveys authorship.
هذا يعكس الأمور،
It suggests that someone is driving.
ويبين فعلا أنه هنالك شخص يقوم بالقيادة.
It's reassuring; people are drawn to it.
إنه لأمر مطمئن يجذب الناس،
Someone making the experience their own.
شخص يقوم بجعل التجربة هذه أمرا خاصا به،
Covering the tragic tune
ليغطي على النبرة المأساوية
with something different,
بشيء آخر،
something radically different.
بشيء مختلف جذريا،
People respond to that.
يتفاعل الناس معه.
Now it seems simple, but actually I think
يبدو الأمر بسيطا الآن، لكني متيقن أنه
in our society and culture in general,
في مجتمعنا وثقافتنا بشكل عام،
we have a huge problem with intent.
توجد مشكلة كبيرة فيما يتعلق بالنيّة.
Now go with me here. Look at this guy. You know who this is?
حسنا دعكم معي هنا، أنظروا إلى هذا الشخص، هل تعلمون من هذا؟
It's Anders Breivik. Now, if he intended to kill
إنه أندرز بريفيك، حسنا، لو كان ينوي أن يقتل
in Olso, Norway last year,
في أوسلو في النرويج العام الماضي
dozens and dozens of young people --
العشرات والعشرات من الشبان،
if he intended to do that,
لو كان ينوي ذلك
he's a vicious criminal. We punish him.
فهو مجرم شرير، سوف نعاقبه،
Life in prison. Death penalty in the United States, not so much in Norway.
الحياة في السجن، عقوبة الإعدام في الولايات المتحدة، ليس تماما كما في النرويج.
But, if he instead acted out of a delusional fantasy,
ولكن لو تصرف بدافع خيال وهمي،
if he was motivated by some random mental illness,
أو قد دفعه لذلك معرض عقلي ما،
he's in a completely different category.
فسوف يكون تحت تصنيف آخر تماما،
We may put him away for life, but
قد نعزله مؤبدا،
we watch him clinically.
ولكن سوف نراقبه طبيا،
It's a completely different domain.
إنه لنطاق مختلف تماما.
As an intentional murderer,
كشخص ينوي القتل،
Anders Breivik is merely evil.
أندرز بريفيك مجرد شرير،
But as a dysfunctional,
ولكن كشخص مختل،
as a dysfunctional murderer/psychotic,
كقاتل مختل مضطرب عقليا،
he's something much more complicated.
إنه شخص أعقد من ذلك بكثير.
He's the breath of some
إنه نافس من
primitive, ancient chaos.
غضب بدائي قديم،
He's the random state of nature
إنه الحالة العشوائية للطبيعة
we emerged from.
التي نشأنا منها،
He's something very, very different.
إنه لشيء مختلف جدا جدا.
It's as though intent is an essential component for humanity.
تبدو النيّة كأنها مركبا ضروريا للإنسانية،
It's what we're supposed to do somehow.
إنها شيء يجب أن نقوم به بشكل أو بآخر،
We're supposed to act with intent.
أفعالنا يحب أن تكون مصحوبة بها،
We're supposed to do things by design.
يجب أن نفعل الأشياء بالتصميم،
Intent is a marker for civilization.
النيّة مؤشر للحضارة.
Now here's an example a little closer to home:
الآن، خذوا هذا المثال القادم من منزلي،
My family is all about intent.
عائلتي قائمة كليا على النيّة،
You can probably tell there are two sets of twins,
كما ترون، يوجد مجموعتان من التوائم،
the result of IVF technology, in vitro fertilization technology,
ناتجتان من تقنية (آي في إف) للتلقيح المختبري،
due to some physical limitations I won't go into.
لأجل بعض القيود الجسدية الخاصة بي والتي لن أسردها،
Anyway, in vitro technology, IVF,
على كل حال، تقنية التلقيح المختبري (آي في إف)
is about as intentional as agriculture.
هي مبنية على النيّة كالزراعة تماما،
Let me tell you, some of you may have the experience.
دعوني أخبركم بشيء قد مر به بعضكم،
In fact, the whole technology of sperm extraction
في الواقع، تقنية استخراج الحيوان المنوي
for spinal cord-injured males was invented by a veterinarian.
لمرضى الحبل الشوكي الذكور اكتشفت بواسطة طبيب بيطري،
I met the dude. He's a great guy.
التقيت شخصيا بالرجل، إنه شخص عظيم،
He carried this big leather bag full of sperm probes for
كان يحمل حافظة جلدية كبيرة مليئة بالمسابير المنوية لجميع
all of the animals that he'd worked with,
الحيوانات التي كان يعمل عليها،
all the different animals.
جميع الحيوانات المختلفة،
Probes he designed,
مسابير صممها بنفسه،
and in fact, he was really, really proud of these probes.
وفي الواقع، كان فخورا جدا جدا بهذه المسابير،
He would say, "You're right between horse and squirrel, John."
ومما قد يقوله "أنت مخلوق يقع بين الخيل والسنجاب يا جون".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But anyway, so when my wife and I decided
لكن على كل حال، عندما قررت أنا وزوجتي
to upgrade our early middle age -- we had four kids, after all --
أن نقوم بتطوير بداية مرحلة منتصف عمرنا، نحن لدينا أربعة أولاد، على كل حال
with a little different technology
عن طريق تقنية مختلفة قليلا
that I won't explain in too much detail here --
لن أسردها بالتفصيل الشديد هنا...
my urologist assured me I had nothing whatsoever to worry about.
لكن طبيب المجاري البولية أكد لي أنه لا يوجد شيء يدعو للقلق:
"No need for birth control, Doc, are you sure about that?"
"لا حاجة لتحديد النسل، أيها الطبيب، هل أنت متأكد؟".
"John, John, I looked at your chart.
"جون جون، لقد نظرت إلى رسمك البياني،
From your sperm tests we can
ومن الاختبارات المنوية،
confidently say that
نستطيع القول بثقة
you're basically a form of birth control."
أنك بسهولة، شكل من أشكال تحديد النسل".
Well!
حسنا!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What a liberating thought! Yes!
يا لها من فكرة تحريرية! نعم!
And after a couple very liberating weekends,
وبعد عطلتي نهاية أسبوعين حرتين،
my wife and I,
أنا وزوجتي،
utilizing some cutting-edge erectile technology
وعن طريق استخدام تقنية انتصاب متطورة،
that is certainly worthy of a TEDTalk someday
والتي حقا تستحق محادثة TED يوما ما،
but I won't get into it now,
لكني لن أدخل في تفاصيلها الآن،
we noticed some familiar, if unexpected, symptoms.
لاحظنا بعض الأعراض المألوفة، بل غير المتوقعة،
I wasn't exactly a form of birth control.
لم أكن شكلا من أشكال تحديد النسل،
Look at that font there. My wife was so pissed.
انظروا خط الكتابة ذلك هنا، زوجتي كانت منزعجة جدا،
I mean, did a designer come up with that?
أعني، هل أتى بذلك مصمم ما؟
No, I don't think a designer did come up with that.
لا، لا أعتقد أن مصمما أتى بذلك،
In fact, maybe that's the problem.
في الواقع، ربما تكمن المشكلة هنا.
And so, little Ajax was born.
وبذلك، ولد أيجاكس الصغير،
He's like our other children,
إنه مثل أطفالنا الآخرين،
but the experience is completely different.
لكن التجربة مختلفة تماما هنا،
It's something like my accident, right?
إنها شيء كالحادث الذي أصابني، حسنا؟
He came out of nowhere.
لقد أتى فجأة،
But we all had to change,
ولكن كان يجب علينا أنت نتغير جميعا،
but not just react to the given;
ولكن ليس بالتفاعل مع المعطى فقط،
we bend to this new experience with intent.
بل بالانحناء لهذه التجربة الجديدة مع النيّة،
We're five now. Five.
نحن خمسة أشخاص الآن، خمسة،
Facing the given with intent. Doing things by design.
نواجه المعطى بالنيّة، وننفذ الأشياء بالتصميم،
Hey, the name Ajax -- you can't get much more intentional than that, right?
يا هذا، بخصوص الاسم أيجاكس، لم يكن بإمكانك أن تكون عالميا أكثر من ذلك، أليس كذلك؟
We're really hoping he thanks us for that later on.
نحن نتمنى حقا أن يشكرنا على ذلك لاحقا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I never became a designer. No, no, no, no. Never attempted. Never even close.
لكني لم أصبح مصمما أبدا، لا لا لا لا، لم أحاول أبدا، ولم أكن قريبا من ذلك حتى،
I did love some great designs as I was growing up:
لقد أحببت بعض التصميمات العظيمة في صغري بينما كنت أتقدم في العمر،
The HP 35S calculator -- God, I loved that thing. Oh God, I wish I had one.
آلة إتش بي 35إس الحاسبة، يا إلهي، كم أحب هذا الشيء، يا إلهي، كم أتمنى لو امتلكت واحدة.
Man, I love that thing.
يا رجل، أحب ذلك الشيء،
I could afford that.
كنت قادرا على الحصول على ذلك،
Other designs I really couldn't afford, like the 1974 911 Targa.
هناك تصميمات أخرى لم يكن بمقدرتي الحصول عليها، مثل سيارة 911 تارجا طراز 1974.
In school, I studied nothing close to design or engineering;
في المدرسة، لم أدرس أي شيء قريب من التصميم أو الهندسة،
I studied useless things like the Classics,
درست أشياء عديمة الفائدة كالأشياء الكلاسيكية،
but there were some lessons even there --
ولكن كانت هنالك بعض الدروس حتى في تلك الأشياء،
this guy, Plato, it turns out he's a designer.
ذلك الشخص، أفلاطون، يبدو أنه كان مصمما،
He designed a state in "The Republic,"
لقد صمم دولة في "الجمهورية"
a design never implemented.
تصميم لم ينفذ أبدا،
Listen to one of the design features
استمعوا إلى إحدى خواص التصميم
of Plato's Government 4.0:
الخاصة بحكومة أفلاطون 4.0:
"The State in which the rulers are most reluctant to govern
"الدولة التي يكون فيها الحكام أكثر الناس ترددا في الحكم
is always the best and most quietly governed,
هي الأفضل دائما والأهدأ محكومية،
and the State in which they are most eager, the worst."
والدولة التي يكون فيها الحكام أكثر الناس رغبة في الحكم هي الأسوأ".
Well, got that wrong, didn't we?
حسنا، لقد فهمنا ذلك بشكل خاطئ، أليس كذلك؟
But look at that statement; it's all about intent. That's what I love about it.
ولكن انظروا إلى العبارة، إنها تتعلق بشكل كبير بالنية، وهذا ما أحب فيها،
But consider what Plato is doing here. What is he doing?
ولكن تأملوا ما يحاول صنعه أفلاطون هنا، ما الذي يصنعه؟
It's a grand idea of design -- a huge idea of design,
إنه مفهوم عظيم للتصميم... مفهموم ضخم للتصميم
common to all of the voices of religion and philosophy
مشترك لدى جميع الأصوات الدينية والفلسفية
that emerged in the Classical period.
التي برزت في الفترة الكلاسيكية،
What was going on then?
ما الذي كان يجري إذن؟
They were trying to answer the question of
لقد كانوا يحاولون الإجابة عن السؤال التالي:
what would human beings do now that they were no longer simply trying to survive?
ما الذي سيفعله بنو البشر الآن بعد أصبحوا لا يجاهدون من أجل البقاء فقط؟
As the human race emerged from a prehistoric chaos,
عندما نشأ العرق البشري من فوضى ما قبل التاريخ
a confrontation with random, brutal nature,
بمواجهة مع طبيعة عشواء قاسية،
they suddenly had a moment to think -- and there was a lot to think about.
أدركوا تماما أنه يجب عليهم التفكير، وكان هنالك الكثير ليفكروا فيه،
All of a sudden, human existence needed an intent.
فجأة، الوجود الإنساني احتاج إلى نيّة،
Human life needed a reason.
حياة الإنسان احتاجت إلى هدف،
Reality itself needed a designer.
الواقع نفسه احتاج إلى مصمم،
The given was replaced
المعطى بُدل
by various aspects of intent,
بجوانب عديدة من النيّة،
by various designs,
بتصميمات عديدة،
by various gods.
بآلهات عديدة،
Gods we're still fighting about. Oh yeah.
آلهات نتصارع حولها للآن، أوه نعم.
Today we don't confront the chaos of nature.
نحن لا نواجه اليوم فوضى الطبيعة،
Today it is the chaos of humanity's impact on the Earth itself that we confront.
بل نواجه اليوم فوضى تأثير البشرية على الأرض التي نجابهها ذاتها،
This young discipline called design, I think,
هذه الضابط الحديث الذي نسميه التصميم، برأيي
is in fact the emerging ethos
هو، في الواقع، الروح الناشئة
formulating and then answering a very new question:
التي تُصوّغ وبعدها تجيب على سؤال جديد:
What shall we do now
ما الذي يتوجب علينا فعله الآن
in the face of the chaos that we have created?
في مواجهة الفوضى التي صنعناها؟
What shall we do?
ما الذي يتوجب علينا فعله؟
How shall we inscribe intent
كيف يمكننا نقش النيّة
on all the objects we create,
على جميع الأشياء التي نصنعها
on all the circumstances we create,
في جميع الأحوال الذي نصنعها
on all the places we change?
في جميع الأماكن الذي نغيرها؟
The consequences of a planet with 7 billion people and counting.
عواقب كوكب يحتوي على 7 بليون شخص ويزيدون
That's the tune we're all covering today, all of us.
هذا هو اللحن الذي نحاكيه جميعا اليوم، جميعنا،
And we can't just imitate the past. No.
ولا يمكننا أن نحاكي الماضي بكل بساطة، لا،
That won't do.
لن ينفع ذلك،
That won't do at all.
لن ينفع ذلك مطلقا.
Here's my favorite design moment:
هذه لحظة التصميم المفضلة لي:
In the city of Kinshasa in Zaire in the 1990s,
في مدينة كينشاسا في زائير في تسعينات القرن العشرين،
I was working for ABC News, and I was reporting on
كنت أعمل لدى وكالة أي بي سي الإخبارية، وكنت أبلغ عن
the fall of Mobutu Sese Seko, the dictator, the brutal dictator in Zaire,
سقوط موبوتو سيكو الحاكم المتسلط، الحاكم المتسلط الوحشي في زائير،
who raped and pillaged that country.
الذي اغتصب ونهب تلك البلاد،
There was rioting in the middle of Kinshasa.
كانت هناك أعمال شعب في وسط كينشاسا،
The place was falling apart; it was a horrible, horrible place,
لقد كان المكان آيلا للسقوط، كان مكانا فظيعا جدا جدا،
and I needed to go and explore the center of Kinshasa
ولقد كان يتوجب علي الذهاب والاستكشاف في وسط كينشاسا
to report on the rioting and the looting.
لأجل الإخبار عن أعمال الشغب والنهب،
People were carrying off vehicles, carrying off pieces of buildings.
لقد كان الناس يسرقون المركبات، ويسرقون أشياء من المباني،
Soldiers were in the streets shooting at looters and herding some in mass arrests.
وكان الجنود في الشوارع يطلقون النار على الناهبين ويشنون بعض حملات الاعتقال الكبرى،
In the middle of this chaos, I'm rolling around in a wheelchair,
وفي وسط كل تلك الفوضى، كنت أتدحرج في الجوار بكرسي متحرك،
and I was completely invisible. Completely.
لقد كنت خفيا عن الأنظار، تماما،
I was in a wheelchair; I didn't look like a looter.
لقد كنت على كرسي متحرك، ولم أبد كناهب من الناهبين،
I was in a wheelchair; I didn't look like a journalist, particularly, at least from their perspective.
لقد كنت على كرسي متحرك، لم أبد كإعلامي، على الأقل من وجهة نظرهم،
And I didn't look like a soldier, that's for sure.
ولم أبد كجندي بالتأكيد،
I was part of this sort of background noise of the misery of Zaire, completely invisible.
لقد كنت جزء كالإزعاج الموجود في الخلفية في معاناة زائير، مخفيا تماما،
And all of a sudden, from around a corner, comes this young man, paralyzed, just like me,
وفجأة، ومن أحد الزوايا، أتى شاب إلي، عاجز عن المشي مثلي تماما،
in this metal and wood and leather
على شيء من المعدن والخشب والجلد،
pedal, three-wheel tricycle-wheelchair device,
أداة هي دراجة ثلاثية العجلات بدوّاسات،
and he pedals up to me as fast as he can.
وكان يتوجه نحوي بأسرع ما يمكن،
He goes, "Hey, mister! Mister!"
ويقول: "هي يا سيد! يا سيد!"،
And I looked at him --
ونظرت إليه...
he didn't know any other English than that, but we didn't need English, no, no, no, no, no.
لم يكن يعرف أي كلمات إنجليزية غيرها، لكننا لم نحتج إلى الإنجليزية، لا لا لا لا لا،
We sat there and compared wheels and tires and spokes and tubes.
لقد مكثنا هناك وقارننا بين العجلات والإطارات والأسلاك والأنابيب،
And I looked at his whacky pedal mechanism;
ونظرت إلى ميكانيكية الدوّاسات المضحكة لديه،
he was full of pride over his design.
لقد كان شديد الفخر بتصميمه،
I wish I could show you that contraption.
أود لو كنت قادرا عرض تلك الأداة الغريبة أمامكم،
His smile, our glow
ابتسامته، والتوهج الذي ينبعث منا
as we talked a universal language
عندما تحدثنا لغة كونية،
of design,
لغة التصميم،
invisible to the chaos around us.
مخفية تماما عن الفضوى من حولنا،
His machine: homemade, bolted, rusty, comical.
أداته: مصنوعة منزليا، مركبّة، يشوبها الصدأ، مضحكة.
My machine: American-made, confident, sleek.
أداتي: أمريكية الصنع، تدل على الثقة، سلسة.
He was particularly proud of the comfortable seat, really comfortable seat
لقد كان فخورا بمعقدها المريح تحديدا، بمقعدها المريح جدا،
he had made in his chariot
الذي صنعه في عربته،
and its beautiful fabric fringe around the edge.
وبحدود قماشها الجميل حول الحافة،
Oh, I wish I'd had those sparkly wheels back then to have shown him, man!
أوه، أتمنى لو كانت لدى الإطارات المضيئة في ذلك الوقت لأريها إياه، يا رجل!
He would have loved those! Oh yeah.
سوف يحبهم! أوه نعم.
He would have understood those;
كان سيفهم ذلك:
a chariot of pure intent -- think about it --
عربة بنيت تماما مع النيّة... فكروا في ذلك...
in a city out of control.
في مدينة خارجة عن السيطرة.
Design blew it all away for a moment.
التصميم سيطر على المكان تماما في لحظة،
We spoke for a few minutes and then each of us vanished back into the chaos.
تحدثنا لعدة دقائق، ثم اختفى كل منا عائدا إلى تلك الفوضى.
He went back to the streets of Kinshasa;
لقد رجع إلى شوارع كينشاسا،
I went to my hotel. And I think of him now, now ...
بينما رجعت إلى الفندق، وأنا أفكر فيه، الآن، الآن...
And I pose this question.
وارمي بهذا التساؤل،
An object imbued with intent --
شيء مشبع بالنيّة...
it has power,
لديه القوة،
it's treasure, we're drawn to it.
إنه لكنز، نحن منجذبون إليه.
An object devoid of intent --
شيء خال من النيّة،
it's random, it's imitative,
إنه عشوائي، إنه تقليدي،
it repels us. It's like a piece of junk mail to be thrown away.
إنه لشيء يصدنا، كرسالة بريدية غير مرغوب فيها ينوى التخلص منها.
This is what we must demand of our lives,
هذا ما يجب أن نطلبه من حياتنا،
of our objects, of our things, of our circumstances:
من أدواتنا، من أشيائنا، من أوضاعنا،
living with intent.
العيش مع النيّة.
And I have to say
ويجب علي القول
that on that score, I have a very unfair advantage over all of you.
أنه بذلك الخصوص، لدي ميزة أتميز بها بشكل غير عادل مقارنة بالجميع منكم،
And I want to explain it to you now because this is a very special day.
وأريد أن أوضحها لكم الآن لأن هذا يوم مميز جدا.
Thirty-six years ago at nearly this moment,
منذ ستة وثلاثين عاما تماما أثناء ما يقارب هذه اللحظة،
a 19-year-old boy awoke from a coma
نهض صبي في التاسعة عشر عاما من عمره من غيبوبة
to ask a nurse a question,
ليسأل ممرضة سؤالا،
but the nurse was already there with an answer.
لكن الممرضة كانت تمكث هناك ولديها إجابة مسبقة:
"You've had a terrible accident, young man. You've broken your back.
"لقد تعرضت لحادث فظيع أيها الشاب، ولقد انكسر ظهرك،
You'll never walk again."
ولن تستطيع المشي مجددا".
I said, "I know all that -- what day is it?"
قلت لها: "أعرف ذلك تماما... أي يوم هو هذا؟"،
You see, I knew that the car had gone over the guardrail on the 28th of February,
انظروا، كنت أعلم أن السيارة اخترقت حاجز الطريق في الثامن والعشرين من فبراير،
and I knew that 1976 was a leap year.
وكنت أعلم أن 1976م كانت سنة كبيسة،
"Nurse! Is this the 28th or the 29th?"
"أيتها الممرضة! هل هذا اليوم هو الثامن والعشرون أم التاسع والعشرون؟"،
And she looked at me and said,
ونظرت إلي وقالت:
"It's March 1st."
"إنه الأول من مارس".
And I went, "Oh my God.
وقلت: "أوه يا إلهي،
I've got some catching up to do!"
لدي أمور علي اللحاق بها!"،
And from that moment, I knew
ومنذ تلك اللحظة، علمت
the given was that accident;
أن المعطى هنا هو الحادث.
I had no option but to make up
لم يكن لدى خيار سوى ممارسة
this new life without walking.
حياتي الجديدة دون المشي.
Intent -- a life with intent --
النيّة... الحياة مع نية...
lived by design,
تعاش بالتصميم،
covering the original
تغطي سابقتها
with something better.
بشيء أفضل.
It's something for all of us to do or find a way to do in these times.
إنه لشيء يجب علينا جميعا فعله أو إيجاد طريقة لفعله في هذا العصر،
To get back to this,
وبالرجوع إلى ذلك،
to get back to design,
بالرجوع إلى التصميم،
and as my daddy suggested a long time ago,
وكان والدي قد اقترح ذلك منذ زمن طويل،
"Make the song your own, John.
"اجعل الأغنية أغنيك يا جون،
Show everybody what you intend."
واري الجميع ما تنوي فعله".
Daddy,
أبتي،
this one's for you.
هذه الأغنية لك.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
♫ Jo Jo was a man who thought he was a loner ♫
♫ جو جو كان رجلا يظن أنه وحيد ♫
♫ but he was another man. ♫
♫ لكنه كان رجلا آخر ♫
♫ Jo Jo left his home in Tucson, Arizona to attend a California bash. ♫
♫ جو جو غادر منزله في توسان بولاية أريزونا ليواجه ليواجه سحقا في كاليفورنيا ♫
♫ Get back, get back, ♫
♫ ارجع، ارجع ♫
♫ get back to where you once belonged. ♫
♫ ارجع إلى المكان التي كنت تنتمي إليه ♫
(Applause)
(تصفيق)